It is a very unique opportunity, I think,
我認為這是一個很難得的機會
for Me to meet you again in Bombay
在你們即將離開這個國家時
when you are all leaving this country,
讓我今天在孟買
and this kind of a special type of a puja
這個特別的崇拜
that we are having today.
與你們重逢
This is the puja done to the sun,
這是敬拜太陽的崇拜
and is called as Makar Sankrant.
稱為”Makar Sankrant”
"Makar" is the tropic of Capricorn,
”Makar”是南回歸線(tropic of Capricorn)
Capricorn is Makar.
南回歸線是”Makar”
So now the sun is moving from the tropic of Capricorn
現在太陽正從南回歸線
towards the tropic of Cancer,
移向北回歸線
and is always a fixed date because it's a,
因為與太陽有關
it has something to do with the sun.
所以這日子是固定的
This is the only date which is fixed in the Indian calendar,
印度曆法，這是唯一固定的日子
because they have to deal with the sun.
因為它與太陽有關
But this time, I don't know why, what has happened
這一次，我不知道為甚麽，甚麽發生了
that they have put it on the fifteenth
他們把它定在這個月的十五號
of this month - it's always the fourteenth.
它通常都在十四號
Now today is, they are changing,
今天，它正在改變
I would say that the seasons are going to be changed.
我是說季節將會轉變
We've got six months when this moves,
因為這種移動，有六個月
sun moves towards the southern hemisphere
太陽移向南半球
and makes it warm, and it comes to the northern hemisphere
令南半球暖和，太陽會移向北半球
from tomorrow.
是從明天開始
So today is the last day, which we say that
所以今天是最後一天
is the day which is the coldest day,
以印度人的理解
according to Indian understanding.
今天是最寒冷的一天
After this the heat will start growing
之後熱力便開始增長
and all the - we can do anything that is auspicious,
我們可以作任何吉祥的事情
any auspicious things can be done after this puja is over,
在這個崇拜後任何吉祥的事情都可以做
during the summer-time.
在夏天
Though it's very hot in summer,
雖然夏天很熱
still people wants the sun to rule us
人們仍想受太陽支配
and to give us warmth because,
想太陽給我們溫暖
because of him only all the fields and all the vegetables,
只因為有太陽，所有田地，所有蔬菜
all the fruits, everything grows.
所有水果，萬物都在生長
And that's why when the six months the sun is not here,
這就是為甚麽當太陽不在這裏的六個月
we call it as "Sankrant,"
我們稱這時候為”Sankrant”
meaning a "calamity" in a way.
意思是災難
That is when of course in the,
當然在歐洲
in the European countries or say in England or America,
例如英國或美國
it is a calamity at that time when the sun is not there.
太陽不在時也是災難
But even here it is regarded as a time today,
在這裏，今天是
it's the day that the end of the Sankrant,
Sankrant,完結的日子
means the end of the calamity is over.
意思是災難完結的日子
And they give something sweet to eat
他們會吃一些
which is also mixed with sesame seeds,
混入芝麻的甜蜜的食品
because sesame seed is heat-giving.
因為芝麻給我們熱量
So today being the coldest day they want to give sesame seed,
所以在今天這個最寒冷的日子，他們想給予芝麻
also want you to retain the heat
也想你保留熱量
and to adjust yourself to the heat that's coming up.
調節自己去適應即將來臨的熾熱
This is all thought of in a way,
這樣想
in a very gross level,
是非常粗略
on a very gross level,
非常粗糙的層次
that we should keep the people warm enough.
我們必須令人保持足夠的溫暖
Also it is said that
也有人說
the warmth of love should be expressed at this time
溫暖的愛必須
for people, because it is the coldest day.
在這時候向人表達，因為這是最寒冷的日子
So they say that "We give you this special thing for you
所以他們說︰「我們給你這特別的東西
to say something sweet" - that is "goad goad bola"
讓你能說一些甜美的話。」就是”goad goad bola”
- means "you say something sweet to us."
意思是你要對我們說一些甜美的話
And the people who live in warm countries are sweeter people
住在溫暖地方的人比
than the people who live in colder places,
住在寒冷地方的人甜美
because the nature is rather very unkind to them.
因為大自然對住在寒冷地方的人很苛刻
I don't blame them for their temperament,
我不會責備這些人的品性
because the nature is so unkind.
因為大自然真的很嚴酷
In India you can live anywhere:
在印度，你可以住在任何地方
you can live under a tree,
可以住在樹下
you can live in a forest,
住在森林
anywhere you can live quite happily,
任何地方你也可以快樂地生活
as long as there is water to drink and water to bathe.
只要有水喝，有水沐浴
And there's not such a problem as
居住在這裏
we have to face in the other parts of the world,
不用面對居住在世界其他地方的問題
where if you have to go out of the house
哪裏若你要外出
you take about fifteen, twenty minutes to dress yourself up.
便要花十五，二十分鐘穿衣
Here you just can walk out of the house,
這裏你立即可以走出屋外
you can keep your houses open during the summer-time,
在夏天，你可以門戶大開
and there's no problem of any kind
大自然沒有給我們
as far as the nature is concerned.
帶來任何麻煩
Nature becomes very kind during summer-time here because
在夏天，大自然變得很友善
the trees are lush and lot of greenery,
因為樹木蒼翠繁茂，非常青綠
people feel very happy during that time,
人們在這時候都感到很快樂
and all the activity becomes more with the sun's energy.
所有活動都與太陽的能量有關
But in the West as you have seen that the sun is much less.
在西方，陽光少得多
Because of that,
因此，
people keep more to their houses,
人們大多會留在屋內
to artificial heating or other heatings,
只利用人功化的熱力或其他熱力
and the doors are closed,
門戶都關上
the hearts are closed,
心扉也關上
and it's difficult for them to
因此他們很難
communicate with other people.
與人溝通
As you go down south more in your countries also,
當你越往你的國家南面走
you'll find people are warmer,
你發現人也越熱情
simpler,
越單純
very hospitable.
非常好客
With the sun you get the heart which is very open heart,
因為太陽，心扉也越開放
and a kind of a inviting heart.
一種邀請你的心
Now if you see on the Sahaja Yoga style,
你現在看看霎哈嘉瑜伽
the sun line is the right side
太陽代表右面
and the moon, moon is the left side.
月亮則代表左面
On the moon line
偏向月亮的人
one can desire but cannot act.
有欲望但沒有行動
Apart from that, on the moon line
除此之外，若過於
if you go too far it can be destructive.
偏向月亮，可以很具毀滅性
Because if you sit in the house doing nothing
因為若你坐在屋內無所事事
- and also these days there's unemployment, say for example,
例如這些日子很多人失業
no work - then you start thinking too much,
沒有工作----你會想得太多
and this thinking is just the desire energy working out,
這種思考只有欲望
no action.
卻沒有行動
And without the action
不作出行動
this energy can become very destructive.
這種力量可以變得非常富毀滅性
That is why we find that people,
這就是我們發現
they say that "empty mind,
當他們說︰「空洞的思維
empty mind is the devil's workshop."
空洞的思維是魔鬼的工作室
Where people have, do not act,
當人只有欲望而沒有行動
when the action doesn't take place,
沒有行動
then it can be quite destructive...
可以很富毀滅性…
So the whole situation is different
溫暖的國家的境況
in a country which is warm,
與不溫暖的國家
and a country which is not warm.
是不一樣的
But in a country where it is very warm also,
在非常溫暖的國家
like Africa,
例如非洲
there are complications due to too much of heat.
因為太熱，情況就很複雜了
Like we have the tropic of -
就像我們有回歸線
mean the equator passing through,
我的意思是赤道通過一個地方
and it heats up that area so much
把哪地方加熱
that it becomes full of jungles,
哪地方因此有很多熱帶密林
very high trees and tall trees;
非常高的樹木
and the whole place is covered with foliage so much
樹葉遮蔽整個地方
that there's no possibility
令陽光
for any sunshine to penetrate through,
不能穿透
and it's quite dark,
因此哪裏很黑
it's full of darkness.
充滿黑暗
So that extreme also comes in the same category
這種極端也在
as the extreme of the cold season.
極之寒冷的季節發生
Now such people live there
居住在哪裏的人
and they, naturally because the sun is less,
很自然因為沒有太多陽光
so they do not grow much;
也不太生長
and they can be primitive people
他們可能是很原始的人
and they can be quite aggressive,
也可能是很有野心
like they learn things from the animals
就像他們從動物身上學習事物
and they could be quite aggressive.
因此他們可能變得很富侵略性
So the balance has to be struck,
所以必須要平衡
and the balance is that,
平衡就是
that we should desire and act.
欲望與行動兼備
But the trouble is in human atmosphere
問題是在人類的
there is a division of labor, I think,
氛圍下有分歧
that one part of the country is thinking,
這個國家的這部分只有思考
another part of the country is acting.
另一部分則只有行動
Under these circumstances nothing works out.
在這種情況下，甚麽也成就不了
So a balance has to be struck where
所以必須有平衡
you have the Sushumna working out.
要處於中脈(sushumna)
Now the Sushumna Nadi is the one where
我們可以說中脈
one would say is the equator - it's not,
中脈是赤道----不，
is not the equator,
不是赤道
but is the axis of the Mother Earth.
是母親大地的軸心
Axis of the Mother Earth is the Sushumna,
母親大地的軸心就是中脈
and that has to act;
它必須行動
and when it comes to that axis then we should understand that we have to be on our axis.
當它來到軸心
So we are on the axis,it is the one that balances.
我們要明白自己必須處於軸心
Actually there is, there is, there is nothing
我們在軸心，這才是平衡
like a big pole
實際上,母親大地內
inside the Mother Earth which we can call it as an axis.
沒有像一支大柱可被我們稱呼為軸心的東西
There is nothing that is material
母親大地內沒有任何物質
inside the Mother Earth that we can call it as an axis,
能被我們稱呼為軸心
but it's the energy force
這是一種能量
which acts in such a manner
當宇宙擴張
that the Earth moves with such tremendous speed
這能量令地球有巨大的
when the cosmos is all spread out so much.
旋轉速度
It not only moves but it creates day and night for us,
它不單在移動，還創造了日與夜
so that day-time we can work and night-time we can sleep,
所以我們白天工作，晚上睡覺
to give us a balance.
這樣令我們平衡
Only also it moves in such a manner round the sun
也是因為地球繞著太陽轉動
that half of the countries get the sun
令一半的國家
during the summer-time,
在夏天取得陽光
and half of them get it during the winter-time.
另一半的國家在冬天取得陽光
That's the axis that acts and works out everything.
軸心就是這樣成就萬事萬物
Apart from that,
除此之外
this axis keeps all the distances necessary
這個軸心令
from other planets and other moving bodies in the cosmos.
各星球和各個在宇宙間移動的物體保持恰當的距離
This axis is the intelligence of the Mother Earth.
這個軸心是母親大地的聰明才智
It is not only the intelligence but it is the fragrance,
不單是聰明，還是芬芳
and apart from, it is the Sushumna Nadi,
除此之外，它是中脈(sushumna nadi)
you can say, of the Mother Earth.
你可以說，母親大地的中脈
Now through this axis only all these swayambhus
透過這個軸心，一切的天然聖石(swayambhus)
and all these great happenings of earthquakes
一切的地震
and all that takes place.
因此發生
This axis is the one which moves.
軸心在移動
It's an energy, we can call it axis as the energy,
它是能量，我們可以稱這軸心為能量
moves the lava into different directions
它令熔岩流向不同方向
and pierces through different areas to create earthquakes,
穿越不同區域令地震產生
and also to have
也令
... volcanoes, volcanoes.
火山，火山
And all these things happen because the axis has sense
所有這一切的發生都是因為軸心
what is to be done.
知道甚麽該做
This axis is the one that loves us.
這軸心愛我們
Because of this axis we,
因為這軸心
we have seasons.
我們有四季
The seasons are created beautifully to give us
它創造漂亮的季節令我們有多樣化
different, different varieties of food
不同種類的食物
and varieties of things.
多樣化的事物
The heat of the Mother Earth if it is lost,
若母親大地的熱力消失
then we'll have nothing on this Earth,
地球便甚麽也沒有
it'll be all frozen and there will be all snow,
全都凍結了，大雪紛飛
and we'll have no food, nothing,
我們便沒有食物，甚麽也沒有
and it will be like moon living here.
就像居住在月球一樣
Now it has been specially created:
特別被創造的是
first the Mother Earth when it was created
首先是母親大地
through the heat of the sun,
當它透過太陽的熱力被創造
so we can say that the sun is the father of the Mother Earth.
我們因此可以說太陽是母親大地的父親
Then she was brought very close to the moon
跟著太陽被帶到接近月球
so it cooled down, absolutely it cooled down,
它因此冷卻，完全的冷卻
it was all snow.
並鋪滿了雪
Then it was brought closer to the sun
之後它被帶到接近太陽
and moved at a point where
帶到生命可以開始
life could start working,
運作的位置
and that's how the whole thing was organized beautifully
這就是整個事件怎樣的漂亮的統籌
to make life grow in that area.
令生命可以在這區域生長
Now when the life started growing,
當生命開始生長
gradually we know that how the carbon was formed.
我們漸漸知道碳如何形成
Now the carbon is formed by the same axis,
碳是由同一個軸心所構成
because there's heat in the axis,
因為軸心內有熱力
the energy of heat that converts
那熱力把
the plants into carbon.
植物轉化為碳
Now this carbon is, later on
遲一些時候，
forms the basis for,
我們
we can say,
可以說
for the production of carbohydrates,
生產碳水化合物的根基
you can say,
你也可以說
or all organic matter.
構成所有的有機物的根基
But to create life we had to have another help,
要創造生命，我們必須有其他的幫忙
is the nitrogen;
是氮
and this nitrogen was also, you'll be surprised to know,
你會很驚訝，氮也是由同一個軸心
that was created by the same axis, by its movement.
同一個移動所創造
And when it created this nitrogen,
當它創造了氮
the nitrogen gave us the amino acids;
氮令我們有氨基酸
and when the amino acids were created within us,
當氨基酸在我們內裏被創造
then we started our lives from amoeba and all that.
我們的生命便從亞米巴原蟲開始
Of course this was done in the ocean,
當然，這是在海洋裏創造的
because in the ocean with the movement,
因為海洋裏的移動
nitrogen was created and life was created,
氮被創造，生命也被創造
and then through the ocean it's emitted out,
跟著透過海洋它擴散開去
and that's how we have amino acids.
這就是怎樣有氨基酸
With the amino acids, the formation of amino acids
氨基酸的形成
gave us the combinations and permutations,
令我們有組合和排列
different lives.
不同的物種
So in the whole evolutionary process
在整個進化過程
the Mother Earth has played a very big part through her axis.
母親大地透過它的軸心扮演著很重要的角色
In the same way in human beings,
同樣對人類
the axis is the most important thing.
軸心是最重要的
That's the main principle of life we have got, is our axis.
我們生命主要的原則，是我們的軸心
We have to stand on our axis.
我們要依賴軸心
Those who do not stand on their axis,
不依靠軸心的人
stand more towards the left or towards the right,
不是偏向左就是偏向右
are capable of complete destruction;
都是步向完全的毀滅
because either they will be destroyed by
因為他們會
too much of right side or too much of left side.
因過分偏右或偏左而被毀滅
So our axis has to be properly dealt with.
所以我們的軸心必須妥善的處理
Now those people who do not have a proper axis
沒有妥當軸心的人
can have problems of different chakras,
他們不同的輪穴
of different kind of quality in a person.
不同的品質都可能會出問題
A person who stretches his axis too much,
過分伸展自己的軸心
puts back his head like this,
把他的頭像這樣放的人
is a person who is very right-sided
是非常偏右脈
and creates problem with his ego;
他是藉由他的自我製造問題
and the one who absolutely bends down
完全屈曲自己
like a slavish person also is a person
卑屈的人
who goes towards his destructiveness.
也是向著毀滅
Now there's a big problem between these two types of people,
這兩類人有一個大問題
one trying to dominate another,
一個想控制另一個
and when they start dominating another person
當他們想控制別人
they actually destroy themselves,
實際是在摧毀自己
as well as destroy the ones whom they are dominating.
也摧毀受他支配的人
For example now,
例如
we have seen that we had
我們曾經見過
Britishers who came here and ruled us.
統治我們的英國人
We have seen the French went and ruled some other people,
我們也見過法國人走到一些地方
then there are Portuguese who went and ruled
統治哪裏的人，跟著是葡萄牙人
some other people.
走到一些地方，統治哪裏的人
But everything that they did to dominate
一切他們想支配的都會有
and all that has double reactions.
雙倍的反效果
First of all by their domination, say,
首先，因為受他們的控制
Indians became very slavish,
例如，印度人變很卑屈
Indians became - even today they are extremely slavish,
印度人…就算是現在他們也是極之卑屈
and they do not have that independent axis
他們沒有應有的
as they should have.
獨立軸心
Extremely slavish people they are.
他們是極之卑屈的人
I mean, especially I've seen in the West,
我的意思是，特別是我在西方見到
I am surprised when the Indians go from here,
我很驚訝從這裏來的印度人
I find they are so very slavish.
我發覺他們都是極之卑屈
They try to sort of do all kinds of slavish acts
他們做盡各種
to please the white-skinned people.
取悅白種人卑屈的行為
The white skin became sort of a very adorable stuff in India.
在印度，白皮膚的人變成很值得敬重的人
That added to the ego of the whites,
這樣令白人的
added to the ego of the whites,
自我更加膨脹
and today you see what's happening is
今天你看到甚麽在發生
all that ego is destroying them.
這個自我在摧毀他們
They are on the verge of destruction because of their ego.
因為自我，他們處於毀滅的邊緣
So it is so unnatural and it is so superficial.
所以這是很不自然，很表面
One has to understand that what is the best
我們要明白人類內在最佳
within a human being is his axis,
的是他的軸心
and everybody has an axis,
每一個人都有軸心
and one must respect the axis of every person.
我們必須尊重每一個人的軸心
In Sahaja Yoga I don't know you by your faces so much;
在霎哈嘉瑜伽，我不太認得你們的樣貌
I know you by your chakras,
我只知道你們的輪穴
by your Sushumna,
你們的中脈
what sort of a Sushumna you have.
你擁有怎樣的中脈
If you have a deep Sushumna, I know you as a deep person.
若你擁有深層的中脈，我便知道你是有深度的人
If you have a superficial Sushumna,
若你擁有表面的中脈，
I know you as a person with a very superficial
我便知道你是個很
type of a Sushumna.
表面的人
And even if you make up something
就算你想裝扮成
by sort of being very nice or good,
非常友善非常好
or talking about Sahaja Yoga
談論霎哈嘉瑜伽
or knowing too much about Sahaja Yoga,
對霎哈嘉瑜伽很認識
and saying things which will baffle normally anyone
說一些通常令人困惑的話
as if you are masters of Sahaja Yoga,
就像你是霎哈嘉瑜伽的導師
I know how deep you are.
但我知道你的程度
So the depth on the axis
所以軸心的深度
is more important than anything else.
比任何都重要
Your axis has to be very deep.
你的軸心必須非常有深度
Now you will say that "Mother,
你會說︰「母親，
the axis is the same as it is, so how can it be deep?"
軸心就是這樣，怎樣可以令它變得有深度？」
So the, in the axis as you see is made in human beings,
人類的軸心，像一張
is like a three-and-a-half coiled paper-like thing,
捲曲成三圈半的紙
and the inside of it is the Brahma Nadi.
內在的是Brahma Nadi(梵天脈)
The Brahma Nadi is a very, very small little,
梵天脈是非常非常細小
we can call a very, very hair-like thing
我們可以說它像頭髮般非常微細
where only a hair-like Kundalini can pass through.
只有像頭髮般的靈量才能通過
But when the person is deep this Brahma Nadi is bigger,
有深度的人，他的梵天脈會大一點
and all the rest of them
其餘互相捲曲的部分
which are coiled into each otherare smaller;
都是很細小的
while the people who are not deep, their outside
沒有深度的人，他們外在
what you call the foldings are bigger
我們稱為可摺疊的
than the inside small thing.
比內在細小的東西大
Now such people could be apparently very dynamic,
這類人表面可能精力充沛
may look very intelligent, may look very smart,
看來很聰明，很精明
may look to be very good-looking
外表漂亮
or whatever it may be outwardly,
不管他們的外在是怎樣
but inwardly they are not deep.
他們的內在卻沒有深度
Inwardly if they are deep,
若他們內在有深度
their whole attitude is beautiful.
他們的態度是很漂亮
They are very joy-giving people,
是給人喜樂的人
they are very joy-giving.
能給人喜樂
And the more if you meet a person of another kind
若你遇見另一類看來很喜樂的人
he may look joyous, he may try to give you joy,
他可能想給你喜樂
but the joy won't be really that deep;
但這種喜樂並非真的那麽深入
it would be like a joy-killing.
只能像是喜樂的屠殺者
So it is important for us to make our axis deeper,
所以要令我們的軸心有深度是非常重要的
and that is where we lack the proper assiduity,
我們就是缺少了適當的刻苦
the proper effort we have to put in.
適當的努力
Now some people have automatically a very deep axis,
現在有些人自動擁有很有深度的軸心
and some people have very, very what you should say,
另一些人則擁有
a very constricted type of the axis.
你所說非常非常…狹隘型的軸心
This axis has to be grown.
軸心必須生長
Now when you come for My puja and all that
當你來我的崇拜
I do expand it, I agree,
我所做的就是擴展它，我同意
but it is temporary thing.
這只能是短暫的
To retain it at that point one has to work at home,
要保持它在這一點上，我們必須在家裏
in the collective also.
在集體裏做點工作
One has to work very much at home with meditation.
必須在家裏多靜坐
But it should be done seriously.
認真的去做
It should not be just a joke,
不能當是玩笑
to be frivolous,
不能輕挑
to be stupid - that's not the way.
不能愚蠢，不能這樣
It should be done very seriously, in the meaning
必須很認真的去做，意思是
that it is a devoted task you have taken,
這是一種虔誠的工作
it's a meditative thing;
要入靜
it's a prayer to God we can call it,
可以說是對神的禱告
it's a puja to God.
對神的崇拜
Is to be done with that reverence,
要以崇敬的態度去做
because reverence is the key of achievement.
因為崇敬是成功的鑰匙
If you have no reverence about yourself
若你對自己
and no reverence of others,
對別人都不尊敬
then it cannot be done.
便不能去做
But first you must have reverence for your own life.
首先你必須對你的生命有尊敬
"What am I doing with my life?
我對我的人生做了些甚麽？
Where am I wasting it?
我在哪裏浪費它？
Why should I waste it?
我為甚麽要浪費它？
Why shouldn't I be deep?
我為甚麽不能有深度？
After all, there must be some purpose of my life.
無論如何，我的人生必須有目標
Am I serving my purpose, am I doing that?"
我是否向著這目標，我有否這樣做？」
All these things if they pop into your head,
若所有這些突然出現在你的腦海中
then you will understand it's very easy to fight out your ego,
你便知道你是很容易與你的自我鬥爭到底
because normally on small, small things people fight.
因為人們通常都為一些小事爭吵
I've seen that in Sahaja Yoga also people fight on things
我曾經在霎哈嘉瑜伽見過
like, I mean which are so useless, absolutely useless.
人們為一些無用的，完全沒用的東西爭吵
To Me it sounds stupid to even mention
就算提及他們怎樣為一些小事爭吵，
the way people fight over small things and quarrel.
我也會感到很愚蠢
But a deep person, even if he doesn't speak much,
一個有深度的人，就算他說話不多
even if he doesn't show off much,
就算他不大炫耀
even if he doesn't sit in the front line,
就算他不坐在前面
he expresses himself through his depth,
他會透過他的深度表達自己
because I can work out better through that.
因為我更能藉由這樣成就事情
So to develop this one must meditate,
要發展這些品質，我們必須靜坐
important thing is to meditate;
靜坐是最重要的
every day, every day, every day.
每一天，每一天，每一天
You may not eat your food one day,
你或許不吃一天
you may not sleep one day,
或許不睡一天
you may not go to your office one day,
或許不上班一天
you may not do anything that you are doing every day
或許不做一天你每天都做的事情
- but you must meditate every day.
但你卻必須每天靜坐
That's an important point,
這是很重要的
to develop the central constricted part into a bigger area.
要把中間狹窄的部分發展成更大的區域
Now when that happens that you start developing it,
當這樣發生，你開始發展它
the first thing you will notice about yourself
你首先發現的是你
that you do not care for any comfort,
不再介意任何舒適
you're not bothered about any,
不再受任何
any material thing.
物質困擾
Whatever it is you are above it,
無論如何，你已超越它
you just don't bother your head - let it be.
你就是不受你的思維困擾，讓它去吧
You just don't want to put your neck
你只是不想把你的脖子
into a thing where you do not belong.
放在不再屬於你的東西上
You just get out of it,
你抽身而出
and you think that
你想︰
"Oh God, this is too much for me, I just don't care for it."
天啊！這對我太過了，我不再介意它了
So your whole attention now moves inward.
你的態度現在向內移
When the attention starts moving inward
當注意力開始向內移
then it expands more.
它擴展得更多
It's the inner part which is called as the Brahma Nadi,
這是內在的，被稱為梵天脈(Brahma Nadi)
and starts expanding and expanding.
它開始擴展，再擴展
Now in small, small things also:
微細的事物也一樣
say for example
就如
if I have not mentioned somebody
若我沒有
and mentioned somebody else,
提及某些人
then they feel,
他們便感到
"Oh, why didn't Mother mention my name?"
「啊！為甚麽母親沒有提及我？」
It's too small a thing that it doesn't matter.
這都是不要緊的小事
As long as you have a deep axis you are with Me,
只要你擁有深度的軸心，你就與我同在
I am with you, absolutely one with each other.
我也與你同在，完全的在一起
But these outward things are,
這些外在的事物
"Oh, She gave a nice sari to another one,
啊！我把一件很漂亮的紗麗給了別人
She never gave us a sari, She didn't do this,
她從不給我們紗麗，她沒有這樣做
didn't do that."
沒有那樣做
All those things if it comes to your head,
若你的腦海裏有這些事情
that means absolutely it's true
代表你有
that there is something lacking in you.
某些缺失
Or if you try to complain,
又或若你想投訴
"Oh, I went there, I had to go by a bus
啊！我到哪裏去，必須坐巴士
and I had to stand on this thing,"
我必須依靠這東西
that shows that you are not comforted at all.
這顯示你不感到舒適
This widening comforts you.
這擴展令你感到舒適
That's the comforting thing,
這是舒適的東西
and that really makes you feel so comfortable
它真的令你
in any circumstance, in any position, in any lifestyle,
在任何境況，任何位置，任何生活模式下都感到舒適
and you do not want to have any other comfort.
你不想有任何其他的舒適
And this one has to develop,
你必須透過靜坐
through meditative effort.
發展這些
Secondly is, we have to know that Sahaja Yoga
第二，我們必須知道霎哈嘉瑜伽
as it is today is a collective happening.
到今天是集體的事件
I find especially among Indian men,
我發覺，特別是印度男子
they never do any work with their hands,
他們從不用雙手做任何事
which is a wrong thing.
這是錯的
Because they don't use their hands at all
因為他們完全沒有運用雙手
their collectivity is poor, very poor.
因此他們的集體很窮，非常窮
Indians have the worst collectivity.
印度人有最糟的集體
If you have an ashram,
若你擁有集體靜室
I don't know why should we build the ashram,
我不知道我們為甚麽要建造一所集體靜室
nobody is going to stay there.
沒有人會留在哪裏
They want to have their own houses,
他們想有自己的房子
their own families,
自己的家庭
their own children;
自己的孩子
they are the worst of all for collectivity.
對集體他們是最差勁的
The reason is, Indian men never do any work with their hands.
原因是印度男子從不用雙手做任何工作
They cannot nail one nail - there are many like that
他們不懂怎樣釘釘子---很多人都是這樣
- leave alone repairing anything.
更不要說其他維修的工作
They will stand with their hands on their hips
他們只會把雙手放在臀旁
and would just tell work to other people, you see.
告訴別人該做甚麽，你明白嗎
There's a Marathi saying,
馬拉塔有這樣的一個說法
a very interesting ....
非常有趣的
that is, "To sit on a camel and to drive the goats."
就是︰「坐在駱駝上，駕著山羊。」
So that is very typical of Indian men.
這就是典型印度男子
They cannot repair anything,
他們不懂修理
they cannot do anything.
不懂做任何事
Now if supposing somebody is spreading something,
若現在有人散播某些東西
they'll just stand like this, watch,
他們只會站著，只在看
they'll never put their hands to it.
從不動手去做
So for every Sahaja yogi it is important
所以對每一位霎哈嘉瑜伽士，這是很重要的
what we call as shramadaan.
我們稱為shramadaan
They have to do some shramadaan.
他們必須做一點shramadaan
"Shramadaan" means the giving of some labor,
"Shramadaan”的意思是付出一點勞動
and that is what we lack.
這是我們缺乏的
That even if it comes to that you'd better clean your house,
就算是要清潔你的房子
you'd better clean the outside of your house,
你最好也清潔房子的外面
try to put some garden around your house,
嘗試在房子周圍種一點植物
try to paint your house,
把房子重新刷上油漆
do some sort of a work with your hand
用雙手做點事
which even if you don't have anything,
就算你沒有房子
you can even brush your hair or something like that.
你也可以整理一下頭髮或做類似的事情
Whatever you think is the easiest you can start with,
只要你認為是最容易做的,就從容易的事情開始吧
because I don't think people even do that.
因為我不認為有人會這樣做
Even they don't shave themselves,
他們甚至不刮鬍子
they get the person to shave them - I mean,
要別人代勞，我的意思是
absolutely lazy lumps as they are.
他們絕對是懶惰的物體
Now, but on the contrary
現在卻相反
we see in the West people use their hands.
你看到在西方，人們運用他們的雙手
Because of that, you see,
因此你便明白
because they can use their hands, they are very collective.
因為他們運用他們的雙手，所以他們很合群
So they score a point on being collective,
他們因為合群而得分
while the Indians score a point because
而印度人卻是因為他們是印度人
they are Indians and they have a heritage
他們祖先的遺產
and they know what is Kundalini,
他們知道甚麽是靈量
they know about Ganesha, they know everything.
知道格涅沙，他們知道一切而得分
So they score a point this side.
他們是在這方面得分
So it's the left side is the desire,
左面是欲望
the right side is the action;
右面則是行動
again we come back to the same position where
我們再次回到原來的位置
we have an imbalance,
我們處於不平衡
that the action takes place in the West,
就是西方有行動
and here is only thinking - "all right, we'll do this"
這裏則只在想，「好吧，我們會去做。」
- planning. Everything is a planning point.
只是計畫，每樣事情都只是在計畫
Nothing works out. You go on planning, planning, planning.
甚麽也成就不了。你不停的計畫，計畫，計畫
Now we are building one single ashram
在過往十年間
in Delhi for the last, I think, ten years.
我們在德里建造一所集體靜室
It is like Taj Mahal, I tell you!
像泰姬陵般，我告訴你
And it's so difficult, you see,
這是很困難的，你要明白
to understand why they have taken so much time
他們為甚麽花這樣長的時間
when it's not a very big place, nothing.
那不是一個大的地方，完全不是
But it is not only the Sahaja yogis but other factors also,
不單因為霎哈嘉瑜伽士，還有其他原因
because everybody is like that, everything is postponed,
因為每一個人都像這樣，每一件事情都延遲
everything is to be done tomorrow.
每一件事都明天才做
"This we will do tomorrow."
「我們明天才做。」
Then one person will come, another person won't come.
一個人來了，另一些人卻沒有來
Like we used to have in the school,
就像我們在學校裏
we would get a sum like that or something to solve that,
通常都是這樣，我們拿到這個數目，或我們這樣解決
see, there were: one house was built,
有房子要建造
three persons came to work and one ran away.
三個人來工作，一個人走了
Then two persons came to work and one stayed
跟著兩個人來工作，一個留下
and two ran away;
其餘兩個跑掉
and then five persons came to work and two persons ran away.
五個人來工作，兩個跑掉
So how, when will the house be finished?
所房子又怎能建好？
Never!
永遠不能
With such runaways it can never be finished.
人這樣跑掉，房子怎能建好
It's like that.
就是這樣
So this is what, where we lack collectivity.
這就是我們欠缺的合群
I was saying that all Indians must find out
我在說所有印度人都必須找找
some place where they could go and plant something.
有沒有可以種植植物的地方
Get hold of some sort of a place
找一處可以
where they could go and plant some nice banyan trees,
種一些榕樹的地方
water it together, work it out together.
一起澆水，一起把事情做好
Now the Indian women are that way better.
現在的印度婦女已經能這樣做
They do lot of work as far as the cooking is concerned
她們在烹調方面做了
and all that,
大量的工作
but the other part is missing.
但其他工作仍然沒有做
The other part is intelligence,
其他是聰明才智
it's the other part is to think.
還有是思考
Now if all the time what they are thinking,
若他們每時每刻都在想︰
"Oh, my husband likes this, I must cook this for him,"
啊！我丈夫喜歡這些，我要為他烹調這些
and now if the husband has to have a, say,
若丈夫進食時要有…例如
a lemon with his food.
檸檬
Now there's no lemon in the house.
現在家裏沒有檸檬
This woman would run up and down all over the place
這位婦女便會到處去
to get the lemon for the husband,
為她的丈夫找檸檬
otherwise he will not eat the food.
否則他不會進食
Doesn't matter,
不要緊
once in a while if he doesn't eat it's all right.
有時他不進食也沒有不妥
But the women will try,
但婦女仍會嘗試
because you see they must keep their,
因為她們想，
they understand one thing
她們明白
that you must keep their palate all right.
你必須要保持他們的味覺妥當
Then they are quite sensible in India
在印度，她們都很合情理
because here they're real tigers,
因為在這裏，他們是真正的老虎
all the husbands are like tigers,
所有丈夫都像老虎
so you have to keep them feeding; otherwise you see,
所以你要不停的餵食他們，否則你便知道
God knows when the tiger will jump on you.
天知道他會何時跳上你的身上
The other way round in England or America I've seen,
在英國或美國卻是相反
the husbands are like,
丈夫像山羊
just like goats and the women are like tigers!
婦女則像老虎
And the Westernized Indian women also are like that,
西化了的印度婦女也是一樣
and when they go to West,
當她們走到西方
even simple women I've seen they become like tigresses.
就算是很單純的女士也會變得像老虎
Something surprising how they change immediately
真的很令人驚訝，她們怎能立即改變
to the position, even if they may not wear the jeans
就算並非穿上牛仔褲
and all those things,
她們就是
but they become like that.
變成這樣
So this imbalancing starts in a human being
當人類
when he doesn't understand
不明白自己是
that you have to be a axis of the Mother Earth,
母親大地的軸心
and neither the Capricorn or the Cancer.
不是南回歸線或北回歸線----人類便會有這種不平衡
This balance comes through our depth,
平衡是藉由我們的深度而來
and that depth has to be improved.
我們要改善我們的深度
Not through just by talking about it,
不是透過空談
by talking about Sahaja Yoga,
空談霎哈嘉瑜伽
but actually seriously doing meditation,
而是認真的靜坐
actually seriously doing meditation.
認真的入靜
Secondly, we must do some collective work.
第二，我們必須做一些集體的工作
Now we have in India, say, architects.
現在在印度，例如，我們有建築師
They have never touched anything with their own hands.
他們從不用雙手觸碰任何東西
They are sitting and drawing, you see, that's all - finished.
只坐著繪圖，你明白，只是這樣
Now after the drawing, do what you like.
繪畫後，喜歡怎樣就怎樣
And now they have problems, practical problems,
現在他們有問題，實際的問題
they cannot nail one nail.
他們甚至不懂釘一顆釘
All are what you call them as white-collar...
他們就是你所稱呼的白領…
Absolutely useless for any handwork.
對用手做的工作完全不懂
They cannot do any handwork whatsoever.
他們不懂做任何手工藝
Even if they have to lift, say, one of these chairs
就算要他們抬起一張椅子
and stretch them, they cannot do it, normally.
再把椅子伸展也辦不到
So under these circumstances one has to understand
在這情況下，
that we come from a society which is absolutely ruinous
對集體來說
as far as collectivity is concerned,
我們是來自一個絕對富毀滅性的社會
so let us be collective.
所以我們要合群
Let us try to do something collective.
讓我們一起做點事
But the collectivity is so poor in India,
印度的集體是太可憐
so poor that even they do not treat their wives nicely.
可憐到他們甚至沒有善待他們的妻子
They'll not talk to their wife nicely,
沒有與他們的妻子
to their children nicely;
與他們的孩子好好說話
to them it is absolutely adharmic to be kind to their wives.
對他們來說，善待他們的妻子是完全不合乎正法(adharmic)
Now the other side is that the Western people
另一方面則是西方人
care so much for collectivity that
對集體過分關注
whatever it is they try to compromise,
無論如何，他們也會嘗試妥協
and try to keep the family life all right.
嘗試令家庭生活妥當
So it's the two extremes as we have.
所以這是兩個極端
Despite that somehow, thanks to the wisdom of Indian women,
儘管如此，不知為何，感謝印度婦女的智慧
the family life is going strong.
令家庭生活很牢固
But if you see such men in England,
若你在英國看到這種男人
I can tell you nobody will stand the nonsense
我可以告訴你，沒有人能忍受
that Indian men do to their women here.
印度男人對他們的婦女所做荒唐的事情
Absolutely, it cannot be forgiven the way they behave.
絕對容忍不了，他們這種言行是絕對不能原諒
So the balance between the women and men:
男女之間的平衡
what is the axis, is the home.
甚麽是軸心，就是家
Home is the axis.
家就是軸心
In the home, what sort of talks you have?
在家裏，你有怎樣的言論？
What do you think about,
你想著甚麽？
what is your problem?
你有甚麽問題？
Where is your attention,
你的注意力放在哪裏？
what do you discuss?
你在討論些甚麽？
That's very important to see.
你要清楚的看到這些是非常重要的
In that you'll find out
你因此能知道
what is going on in the family.
甚麽發生在你的家庭
Say you are talking ill of each other,
例如你們互相批評
if you are telling your child against your husband,
若你向你的孩子說些批評丈夫的話
husband is telling the wife against,
丈夫亦批評妻子
telling the children about, against the,
告訴孩子這些
against the husband, like that.
批評的說話
If it is going on like that,
若這種情況持續
then what happens,
甚麽會發生
that there cannot be the axis which is all right.
這不可能是妥當的軸心
The axis is love,
軸心是愛
but not exploitation nor spoiling - it's love.
沒有剝削，沒有溺愛，只是愛
In country like ours, you see, what is the axis we have?
像我們的國家，你看到，我們擁有怎樣的軸心？
The axis of our country is adhyatma.
我們的國家的軸心是adhyatma
We have to now get over this hankering after money,
我們現在要克服對金錢
development, this, that. First take to adhyatma.
對社會發展，對這些那些的渴求，首先要有adhyatma
If people get realization before they are developed,
若人在得到自覺後社會才發展
there won't be the problem of creating another America here.
那麽，在這裏創造另一個美國就不再是問題了
We don't have to become communist,
我們不需要成為共產主義者
we don't have to do anything like that,
不需要做這樣的事情
because communists are just the same as Americans,
因為共產主義者就像美國人
there's no difference at all in temperament.
他們本質上毫無分別
If an American is allowed to stay in Russia
若一個美國人獲准留在俄羅斯
he'll behave the same way as a Russian behaves,
他的言行與俄羅斯人會完全一樣
and if a Russian is sent to America
若送一個俄羅斯人到美國
he behaves the same way as the Americans behave.
他的言行便與美國人一樣
There's no change at all.
完全沒有任何分別
Now if the axis of adhyatma in any country
若adhyatma的軸心，對任何國家的
where a person achieves his spiritual ascent
靈性昇進有成就的人來說
is, becomes the most important thing and is achieved,
變得最重要，亦已經成就了
then any amount of development,
那麽，任何的社會發展
any amount of all these things
任何種類的發展
cannot destroy that country,
也不能摧毀這個國家
cannot create wars.
也不會有戰爭
There will be peace everywhere,
處處都會很和平
there will be enjoyment everywhere.
處處都有樂趣
So on this day of Makar Sankrant
所以在今天這Makar Sankrant的日子
let us say now the Sankrant is over,
讓我們現在就說Sankrant(災難)已經結束
and we have to look forward to the new age
我們期望新的年代的
of a new moon blessing us,
新月能祝福我們
and the great sun coming over
偉大的太陽來到
to give us all the energy we need,
給予我們需要的能量
to celebrate the advent of the golden age of Sahaja Yoga.
慶祝霎哈嘉瑜伽黃金年代的來臨
May God bless you all.
願神祝福你們
Now for the puja,
至於崇拜
the Makar Sankrant Puja is very little,
Makar Sankrant 是一個小崇拜
it's the puja of the Surya Devata, I don't know ...
是對太陽神蘇利耶(Surya Devata)的崇拜,我也不知道…
From the foreign country,
來自國外而
who is going to stay after the
十一號之後仍留這裏的人
11th, that is on the 12th? On the 12th - after the 12th.
在十二號嗎？在十二號，十二號之後
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten ...
一、二、三、四、五、六、七、八、九、十…
seventeen, eighteen, nineteen, twenty.
十七、十八、十九、二十
All right, let's put it,
好，這樣吧
who is going to stay in Bombay after the 11th?
誰會在十一號後仍留在孟買？
When are these people going?
這些人甚麽時候走？
Those who are going to stay in Bombay after the 11th,
有誰在十一號後還留在孟買
when are they going, when are you going?
他們甚麽時候走？
You are coming to Pratishthan. All right.
你要去Pratishthan，好吧
What about you, John?
約翰，你又怎樣？
Do you want to stay here in Bombay,
想留在孟買嗎
or you want to stay in Pratishthan?
又或你想留在Pratishthan？
I mean, there's no arrangements here,
我的意思是這裏沒有
so all those who are not going on the 11th or 12th,
為你們作任何安排，所有在十一或十二號
like that, in the near future,
或短期內不離開的人
how many are those who are going to stay longer?
有多少人想多留一會兒？
About thirty-four. How many men and how many ladies?
大約三十四人，有多少男多少女？
So we have decided that the men can come to Pratishthan,
我們決定男士到Pratishthan
and the rest of the ladies can go to Alibagh.
女士則到Alibagh
The reason is Pratishthan is still extremely spartan.
因為Pratishthan 紀律性仍然很強
It's not meant for ladies at all,
完全不適合女士
and I have only one room where I live.
我住的地方只有一間房間
So best thing would be to send all the ladies...
所以最好把所有女士送到…
Let them go to Alibagh,
讓她們到Alibagh
and let them pay for their stay in Alibagh
她們要支付留在Alibagh的費用
to people who will be looking after them.
付給照顧她們的人
Those who are coming to Pratishthan,
有多少人到Pratishthan？
how many there are? The rest of the men, about fifty.
大約五十位男士
Fifty, all right.
五十位，好吧
So when are you going back with the whole thing?
你們甚麽時候回來？
You see, because it's such a liability, this work.
你要明白，這是一種負擔
You can come to Pratishthan
若想拍照
if you want to take some photographs or things,
你可以到Pratishthan
but it's a liability for us because,
但對我們這是一種負擔
you see, unless and until you go back,
你要明白，除非你回去
it will be a liability on our head all the time.
這會是我們的負擔
So best thing is that you come to Pratishthan,
所以最好你可以到Pratishthan
do a little photography or whatever you want to do.
拍一點照片，或做你想做的事
And then you'd better book yourself,
最好是你自己安排
because this must go out of our country,
因為這將是在國外
otherwise they're always on our head,
不然，這將是我們的負擔
and they are following us.
他們跟隨著我們
So I am sorry, but you'll have to go with this ...
我很抱歉，你必須與…
stuff that you are carrying.
帶走你帶來的東西
So we will have to do it in three, four days' time.
你們要在三四天內完成
You can finish the photography there,
把照片拍好
and you fix up your going.
快準備吧
So for all the ladies who are going to stay on,
那些留下來的女士
can go in Washi or can go to Alibagh.
可以到Washi或Alibagh
Alibagh is better...
到Alibagh較好
They can go to Alibagh and stay there in Alibagh,
他們可以到Alibagh留下
about thirteen or fourteen ladies...
有約十三四位女士
All right, so done.
好吧，就這樣吧
Now let's ... Atharv, Ganesha ...
現在就讓…Atharv Ganesha…
Twenty-one people from America have to go,
來自美國的二十一個人要離開
so we'll try to finish the puja as soon as possible,
我們要盡快完成崇拜
and they can leave.
他們便可以走了